A Guide to the Legislative Petitions of the General Assembly, 1776-1865
Library of Virginia
Private Relief/Compensation - There are 1,931 records in the database from citizens, administrators, sheriffs, deputy sheriffs, commissioners of the revenue, securities, militia officers, tobacco inspectors, clerks, school commissioners, teachers, executors, jailors, justices of the peace, merchants, and others asking for private relief or compensation. The petitioners within this category seek compensation for services to the state, the education of indigent children, the loss of tobacco stored in inspection warehouses, overpayment of taxes, impressments of horses to convey prisoners & hospital inmates, land taken for the use of the Commonwealth, the loss of slaves who were tried & convicted of crimes, the loss of military certificates, the collection of revenue, labor on roads, expenses of jailors, the apprehension of escaped convicts, damages to lands from internal improvements, erroneous assessments, and merchants' licenses.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: various citizens of Southampton County asking for compensation for slaves lost during Nat Turner's Insurrection (1831); John H. Allstadt asking for compensation for two slaves lost during John Brown's Raid (Jefferson Co. - 1860/01/09); Adam Baird & Andrew Hosea asking for a law appropriating a sufficient sum for the discharge of their judgment & warrant for work done by them on the Capitol (Richmond City - 1806/12/05); Anderson Barrett asking for compensation for work done on the Capitol (Richmond City - 1842/01/27); Chang & Eng, Siamese twin brothers, asking for relief from the law imposing a tax on them in every county, city, borough, or corporation they perform (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1832/03/12); Citizens of Jefferson County asking for a bill for the relief of Walter Shirley who served as foreman of the jury that convicted the late insurgents of Harpers Ferry and whose barn was destroyed by a fire after the trial (1860/01/12); Alexander Dromgoole asking for a law authorizing the payment of a sum of money for his service with Andrew Moore to meet with the chiefs of the Cherokee Nation (Washington Co. - 1818/12/28 & 1825/12/08); Samuel Freeman asking for compensation for his services in making arrangements for the celebration of the victory at Yorktown and the visit of General Lafayette in 1824 (Richmond City - 1833/01/23 & 1847/02/01); Samuel Griffin asking for compensation for his lot which was taken by the Commonwealth for the purpose of erecting the Capitol (Richmond City - 1795/11/22); Thomas McClelland asking for compensation for plans submitted by petitioner for the proposed Washington monument in Richmond (Alexandria Town - 1850/02/13); Samuel Overton asking for additional compensation for his land condemned by ad quod damnum for the use of the public for the establishment of a Manufactory of Arms (Richmond City - 1789/12/05); James Paxton, Commandant of the Public Guard at the Lexington Arsenal, asking for compensation (Rockbridge Co. - 1819/12/17, 1825/12/08, 1826/12/07, & 1852/01/27); John Reveley asking for compensation for his services in erecting & managing a foundry at Westham (Henrico Co. - 1778/10/14 & 1780/12/11); George William Smith, prosecutor on the part of the Commonwealth in the County, asking for compensation for his services in fifty-nine called courts upon the trials of negroes or slaves charged with conspiracy & insurrection against the Commonwealth (Henrico Co. - 1800/12/06); Trustees of the Nottoway Indians asking for relief for a debt owed by them to the Commonwealth (Southampton Co. - 1822/12/14); Philip Turpin asking for restoration of his donation of two acres lying around the Council Chamber for the purpose of erecting public buildings to be erected for the residence of the governor (Richmond City - 1788/11/22, 1791/11/11, 1794/11/24, & 1811/12/06); Charles L. Wingfield asking for a law authorizing the Treasurer to pay him the value of a certain lot which was condemned for the use of the Penitentiary in Richmond and for the use of the property from 1819 to the present (Norfolk City - 1837/01/23 & 1838/01/08); and Alexander Wylly asking for compensation for services as Keeper of the Capitol and for transferring records from Williamsburg to Richmond (Williamsburg City - 1780/05/22).
Prohibition/Temperance - There are 301 records in the database from citizens, temperance societies & organizations, voters, and others regarding the prohibition of the manufacture & sale of liquor in Virginia. In addition, there are petitions concerning the distillation of grain, acts of incorporation of temperance societies such as the Sons of Temperance, the licensing of ordinaries, and the sale of liquor to slaves & free negroes.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: General Temperance Assembly asking for a law for taking the sense of the people at the polls as to the propriety of continuing the sale of intoxicating liquors (Richmond City - 1849/01/09); Inhabitants of Berkeley County asking that the Legislature do something about the dreadful effects of drunkenness in every department of society (1818/12/26); President & Professors of Washington College and Superintendent of Professors of the Virginia Military Institute asking for additional penalties upon venders of spirituous liquors to students of the colleges & academies of the Commonwealth (Rockbridge Co. (1846/12/14); and the State Temperance Convention asking for a law to authorize the qualified voters in each county, city, & incorporated town to determine whether licenses to retail ardent spirits shall be issued in their respective localities (Richmond City - 1848/01/10).
Railroads/Railroad Companies - There are 913 records in the database from citizens, railroad companies, contractors, committees, stockholders, conventions, coal miners, and others regarding the capital stock of railroad companies, the construction of railroads, the extension of railway lines, the incorporation of railroad companies, grants of right of way, loans, and changes in the termination of railroads. Included are petitions from the following railroad companies: Baltimore & Ohio Railroad; City Point Railroad Company; Portsmouth & Roanoke Railroad Company; Louisa Railroad Company; Orange & Alexandria Railroad Company; Richmond & Petersburg Railroad Company; Richmond, Fredericksburg, & Petersburg Railroad Company; Winchester & Potomac Railroad Company; Richmond & Danville Railroad Company; and others.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Baltimore & Ohio Railroad Company asking for aid from the state for the construction of part of the railroad which will pass through Virginia (Berkeley Co. - 1838/03/08); Citizens of Alexandria County protesting against any further legislation for the Washington & Alexandria Railroad (signed by Robert E. Lee) (1858/01/06); and Proceedings & resolutions of the Rail Road Convention held at Clarksburg regarding a memorial from citizens of the North-Western part of the state to authorize an extension of the Baltimore & Ohio railway through their territory (Harrison Co. - 1845/12/02).
Revenue/Taxation - There are 1,649 records in the database related to revenue & taxation. Included are petitions for citizens, sheriffs, deputy sheriffs, administrators, securities, executors, commissioners of the revenue, merchants, clerks, tax collectors, escheators, agents, traders, coroners, pilots, and others. These petitions concern refunds of taxes paid, reduction of taxes or tolls, relief from judgments & fines for nonpayment of taxes, compensation for commissioners of revenue, sheriffs & deputy sheriff's collection of taxes, land assessments, license taxes, tax exemptions, taxes on dogs, pilotage, delinquent taxes, revenue laws, militia fines, and wharfage fees.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Samuel Allison, Consul of the United State for the city of Lyons, France, asking for ten years to pay the delinquent taxes owed by his for lands conveyed to him by the late Col. James Swan of Boston (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1832/01/09); Chang & Eng, Siamese twin brothers, asking for relief from the law imposing a tax on them in every county, city, borough, or corporation they perform (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1832/03/12); Citizens of Richmond asking for a system of discriminating taxation upon the manufacturers & imports of the Free-Soil states, a plan of building up commercial marine, & other purposes (1860/01/11); Citizens of Lexington asking that the trustees of the town may be authorized to impose a tax on real property for the purpose of bringing water into the town (Rockbridge Co. - 1832/12/05); Dissenters asking for the disestablishment of the Church of England and freedom from taxation for religious purposes (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1776/10/16); Inhabitants of the County & Borough of Norfolk asking for relief from the payment of taxes as a result of the depredations suffered during the late invasion (1781/12/08); Charles Carter Lee, Sidney S. Lee, & Robert E. Lee, heirs of Gen. Henry Lee, asking for relief in settling the delinquent taxes on a large tract of land purchased by their father in 1796 from John Nicholas (1831/12/19); D. H. London, President of the Southern Rights Association of Virginia, asking for excise laws discriminating in favor of articles grown, manufactured, or imported from Virginia (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1851/01/31); and Josiah Shanklin asking for permission to sell his invention the "Mechanics Companion" in the Commonwealth without a license and tax thereon (includes broadside) (Wood Co. - 1855/02/01).
Roads/Turnpike Companies - There are 2,507 records in the database from citizens, turnpike companies, road commissioners, contractors, stockholders, trustees, and others regarding roads and turnpike companies. These petitions relate to compensation for work on roads, construction of turnpike roads, amendments to charters, acts of incorporation, capital stock, tolls & toll gates, appropriations, lotteries, compensation for labor on roads, exemptions from working on roads, road repairs, extension of time to complete roads, changes to turnpike routes, extensions to roads, road laws, macadamizing of roads, bridges, compensation for damages caused to landowners by road construction, and the widening & straightening of streets within towns & cities. Includes are petitions from the following turnpike companies: Manchester & Petersburg Turnpike Company; Manchester Turnpike Company; Ashby's Gap Turnpike Company; Fauquier & Alexandria Turnpike Company; Leesburg Turnpike Company; Lexington & Covington Turnpike Company; Little River Turnpike Company, Lynchburg & Salem Turnpike Company, Pittsylvania & Lynchburg Turnpike Company; Blue Sulpher Springs Turnpike Company; Richmond Turnpike Company; Salem & Peppers Ferry Turnpike Company; Smithfield, Charlestown, & Harpers Ferry Turnpike Company; Swift Run Gap Turnpike Company; Valley Turnpike Company; Kanawha & Fayette Turnpike Company; Lynchburg & Salem Turnpike Company; Staunton & James River Turnpike Company; Wellsburg & Washington Turnpike Company; and others.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Thomas B. Bond, owner of a lot & tenement in Petersburg, asking for a law allowing a proposed street to be opened (includes map) (1843/01/16); Citizens of Lexington, sufferers from the fire of 1796, asking that the law passed to authorize a lottery for their relief may be modified so as to appropriate money towards opening a road over the North & South Mountains and building a public schoolhouse (Rockbridge Co. - 1801/12/16); Charles Dimmock, Captain & Superintendent of the Armory, regarding the petition of the Council asking for two street ways and a change in the location of a third across the Armory grounds (Richmond City - 1852/05/29); Inhabitants of Norfolk Borough asking for an appropriation of the Common Hall for any other part of the expense that what shall be requisite for graduating the streets, preparing the ground for receiving the pavement, & for paving the intersections of the streets (1805/12/18 & 1806/12/03); Inhabitants of Norfolk Borough asking for an act to authorize the court to cause Washington Street to be opened & extended at its present width from its termination on the western side of Boush Street until it intersects with Duke Street (includes plat) (1817/12/03); Ministry & vestry of Fairfax Parish asking that their place of worship may remain secured to the Protestant Episcopal Church in Alexandria and that their dead be permitted to rest in their graves without danger of being disturbed by the proposed extension of the streets in Alexandria (Fairfax Co. - 1785/11/15); President & Common Council of Richmond City asking for a law establishing all the streets in that part of the city added to the town on the eastern boundary (1806/12/04); and the Select & Common Council of Norfolk City asking for such amendments to an act of 27 February 1833 as will give authority to erect a City Hall on the Public Square and to open a street on the southern boundary of the square (1846/12/14).
Schools/Universities - There are 889 records in the database from colleges, universities, academies, school commissioners, teachers, orphan asylums, citizens, committees, faculty, trustees, professors, students, visitors, and others. The petitions within this category deal with compensation for the education of poor children, acts of incorporation, appropriations & loans, lotteries, the Literary Fund, the education of free negroes, paying teachers of the Christian religion, sale of lands, appointment of trustees, public education, common school system, free schools, and the erection of school buildings.
Noteworthy are the following: Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia proceedings & resolution regarding the increase of disease at the University and the suspension of lectures (Albemarle Co. - 1858/03/22); Robert Briggs & others asking for the incorporation of the Medical College of Virginia (Richmond City - 1835/12/23 & 1836/12/31); Cadets of the Virginia Military Institute asking for an appropriation to reconstruct & enlarge their barracks (Rockbridge Co. - 1849/01/03); Citizens of Albemarle County asking for an appropriation to erect a marble statue in honor of Thomas Jefferson at the University of Virginia (1850/12/04); Citizens of Albemarle County who served as jurors in the case of John S. Mosby, a student in the University, convicted of unlawful shooting of George Turpin, asking that he be pardoned & have a fine remitted (1854/01/14); Citizens of Rockbridge County asking for the reorganization of the Lexington Arsenal into an institution of military instruction & education (1839/01/19, 1836/01/19, & 1836/01/13); Free persons of color in Fredericksburg asking for an act authorizing a school for the instruction of free people of color (Spotsylvania Co. - 1838/03/16); Thomas Hudgins & others asking for the incorporation of Richmond College (Richmond City - 1840/01/02); Jefferson & Washington Societies of the University of Virginia asking for an act of incorporation (Albemarle Co. - 1840/02/08); Richard Lorton asking for permission to use the Museum on the Public Square for an Athenaeum (Richmond City - 1833/02/14); Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen, & Common Council of Williamsburg asking for permission & authority to raise by lottery a sum to be applied towards repairing the Capitol & building annexed to it, and establishing a fund for the support of the academy (1783/05/27); President & Professors of Washington College and Superintendent of Professors of the Virginia Military Institute asking for additional penalties upon venders of spirituous liquors to students of the colleges & academies of the Commonwealth (Rockbridge Co. (1846/12/14); Rector, Visitors, & Governors of the College of William & Mary asking that a fund may be established for the support of the college (Williamsburg City - 1777/05/28); Residents of Norfolk City asking for an act to incorporate a school called the "House of Jacob" for teaching the Hebrew & German languages (1852/12/14); Society of Friends asking for the modification of the laws prohibiting the education of free negroes (Alexandria - 1848/02/26); and Trustees of the Theological Seminary of Virginia asking to be incorporated for the education for poor & pious young men in the ministry of the gospel (Prince Edward Co. - 1815/12/07).
Slaves/Slavery - There are 1,139 records in the database related to slaves & slavery. Included are petitions from slaves, former slaves, citizens, heirs, administrators, slave owners, colonization societies, executors, jailors, overseers of the poor, Quakers, and others respecting permission of freed slaves to remain in the state, permissions by slave owners to bring slaves into the state, wills & administrations, compensation of slave owners for the loss of their slaves, manumissions, general emancipation, colonization of slaves in Africa, runaways, pardons, insurrections, and commerce with slaves.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: John H. Allstadt asking for compensation for two slaves lost during John Brown's Raid (Jefferson Co. - 1860/01/09); Board of Managers of the Virginia Colonization Society asking for a charter to obtain a tract of land on the coast of Africa for the establishment of a new plantation called New Virginia, to be settled by free people of color & emancipated slaves (Henrico Co. - 1837/01/19); Citizens of Culpeper asking for a law prohibiting any slave, free negro, or mulatto to learn a trade or art under severe & onerous penalties upon the owner (1831/12/09); Citizens of Cumberland County asking for enactments in aid & defense of the trade, industry, proprietary and political rights of the people of the Commonwealth involved in the institution of negro slavery in the states where that institution now exists (1860/01/05); proceedings of a public meeting of citizens of Greene County in favor of Virginia dissolving her connection with the Federal Government, taking public property in Washington, securing a Convention, ridding the state of free negroes, etc. (1861/01/19); Citizens of Hancock County & elsewhere asking for reforms in the laws concerning slaves & free persons of color to protect the parental relation, to recognize the marital relation, & to allow persons so disposed to teach persons of color to read (1856/02/27); Citizens of Hanover County & elsewhere asking for the total prohibition of emancipation, except upon removal from the state, and the immediate classification of the free blacks, and requiring at stated periods their removal (1831/12/11 & 1831/12/14); Citizens of King & Queen County asking for the repeal of the law for freeing negroes, and that in the future, no negroes be freed except for meritorious services (1800/12/02); Citizens of Loudoun County asking for energetic & prudent measures for the ultimate extinction of involuntary servitude and the removal of a race irreconcilably antagonistic to petitioners (1831/12/23); Citizens of Richmond & Henrico asking for the incorporation of a Society for the Protection of Slave Property in Henrico & Richmond (Richmond City - 1842/03/08); Directors of the Eastern Lunatic Asylum asking for certain amendments to the existing laws regulating their institution including allowing slaves & lunatics from other states into the asylum (Williamsburg City - 1845/12/02); Peter Edwards asking for compensation for the loss of three slaves during the late insurrection (Southampton Co. - 1831/12/12); Females of Augusta County asking for the extinction of slavery for fear of rebellion (1832/01/19); Inhabitants of Botetourt County asking for an amendment to the U.S. Constitution which will give Congress power to raise & appropriate money to transport free negroes & slaves to the coast of Africa (1832/01/04); Inhabitants of Brunswick County asking that no act may pass for the general emancipation of slaves and that the act passed on 6 May 1782 entitled "an act to authorize the manumission of slaves" be repealed (1785/11/10); James, a slave belonging to William Armistead who entered the service of the Marquis de Lafayette, asking to be granted his freedom (New Kent Co. - 1786/11/30); documents relating to the claim of Edmunds Mason & Williamson Pair for guarding prisoners during the insurrection (includes list of prisoners) (Greensville Co. - 1833); Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen, & Commonalty of Petersburg asking for an annual state lottery to diminish the number of slaves annually by purchase in the proportion of two females to one male, and disposing of them in other states or other countries as indentured servants (1805/12/11); Quakers asking that citizens be legally authorized manumit their slaves in such manner as will prevent injury to the community (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1780/11/29); Quakers protesting against slavery, and specifically the treatment of emancipated slaves (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1782/05/29); Religious Society of Friends asking for the interference of the Legislature for remedying abuses in the traffic of slaves from, or through, Virginia to other states (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1802/12/17); Pharoh Sheppard, former slave who informed his master of an impending insurrection, asking for an ac emancipating his son Pharoh (Richmond City - 1810/12/14); George William Smith, prosecutor on the part of the Commonwealth in the County, asking for compensation for his services in fifty-nine called courts upon the trials of negroes or slaves charged with conspiracy & insurrection against the Commonwealth (Henrico Co. - 1800/12/06); and Francis Viggo, resident of Vicennes in the state of Indiana & native of Italy, asking for compensation for eighty-seven slaves who escaped to Lord Dunmore's fleet from his father's property at Willoughby Point (includes list of slaves) (Norfolk Co. - 1777/06/03).
Tobacco Inspection/Industry - There are 776 records in the database from tobacco inspectors, citizens, owners & proprietors of tobacco warehouses, cultivators of tobacco, tobacco manufacturers, merchants, traders, pickers of tobacco, and others. The petitions relate to the establishment of warehouses for the inspections of tobacco, additional salary for tobacco inspectors, compensation for tobacco destroyed or stolen from inspection warehouses, protests against the establishment of tobacco inspections, funds for the construction of tobacco warehouses, tobacco laws, increases in the rent or rates of storage, discontinuance & revivals of tobacco inspections, payment of taxes in tobacco, and tolls.